Slim Ouertani June-81, Tunisian

ouertani@gmail.com • 00966583012381 • Riyadh (*Saudi Arabia*) linkedin.com/in/ouertani • ouertani.github.io • jroller.com/ouertani • twitter.com/ouertani

Senior Architect

Summary

Slim Ouertani is enterprise and solution architect, InfoQ-Fr editor, Big Data Science, Cloud and SOA Certified trainer , founder and organizer of Riyadh IT Architecture Meetup. After his engineer's degree in computer science, Slim spent over than 15 years in multinational companies such as Orange, Sagem, and GE as architect, international agile coach and Head of IT development department. His main role was to build, design and collaborate in the development of enterprise solutions.

Slim regularly contributes to InfoQ-FR community where he is the author of many articles and news. He's broad certified as in addition to his SOA, Cloud and Big Data Science certifications: Trainer, Architect & Engineer, Slim holds multiple certifications including Togaf 9, Archimate 2, IT4IT, SABSA, PMP, ITIL, CMMi, Mongo, Spring, JAVA, SCALA and reactive programming...

Slim enjoys open source contribution and invite you to follow him on twitter @ouertani.

Experience

GE Digital

Senior Architect

Riyadh, SAUDI ARABIA 06-2019 – present

• Drive growth, improve efficiency and customer satisfaction in the health care digital transformation journey.

machinestalk

Riyadh, SAUDI ARABIA

CTO 03-2017 – 05-2019

- key contributor in the company transformation to be top ranked IoT service provider kingdom wide
- Responsible of the technology strategy implementation, Technology alliance
- Responsible of building and implementing the new IoT framework.

Al-Elm Information Security

RIYADH, SAUDI ARABIA

06-2014-03-2016

- **Solution Architect**
 - Member/Founder of ELM Development Architecture Center of Excellence.
 EPC committee member responsible of the architecture models, eversee.
 - EPG committee member, responsible of the architecture models, oversee the process architecture, approve it and ensuring the process improvement.
 - Architecting and Designing enterprise solutions using diverse technology stack
 - Work with peers to conduct Solution Architecture Reviews for a broad set of projects
 - Review and provide input into functional & non-functional requirements
 - Provide consulting and conduct reviews through the development lifecycle
 - Defining the Architecture and guiding the use of various tools, technologies and techniques in the realization of that Architecture:
 - HIS system architecture, SDP, WASL,...
 - EA Riyadah, API GWT, Microservices...
 - Create and maintain a set of standard practices, patterns and anti-patterns and ensure the appropriate usage of that.

Sofrecom (Orange FT Group)

Tunis, Tunisia 03-2013 – 06-2014

Software Architect, International Agile Coach Manage and direct virtual distributed teams

- Make or Buy Analysis
- Establish regular meetings to review technical designs and provide mentoring and guidance
- Mentor development teams on different architecture and design paradigms or practices
- Maintain a knowledge base of emerging technologies and products
- Scrum Master, Enterprise Architect

Zenika JEE Architect

Paris, FRANCE

12 - 2012 - 03 - 2013

• Client: Bouygues Telecom

- Project: Home Automation (2 months)
- BBox embedded automation solution communicating with centralized system

• Client: SwissPost

Project: Image Plus (2 months)

Online outsourcing solution for picture processing.

Orange Tunis, Tunisia

Head of Development and Tools Manager

01-2010 - 11-2012

- Architecture, development and implementation of a web service platform:
- IN/AIR, BSCS/CMS/Data Charging/CRM/IVR/USSD Development of the "after sales service" solution
- Launch of BI departement
- Different applications: inter systems and synchronization platforms, web application...

Sagem Software & Technologies

Tunis, Tunisia

Solution Architect

06-2009 - 01-2010

 Architecture design and integration of a communication server and administration of remote gateways.

03-2008 - 06-2009**Solution Architect**

- Modular OSGi Server architecture under Linux platform responsible for controlling and interacting with electricity counters in order to retrieve statistics and have data storing/manipulation via different technologies and frameworks
 - DISTRIBUTED COMPUTING, Cryptography

Solution Architect & Team Leader

12-2007 - 03-2008

Designing an SOA architecture and implementation of an Intranet service for human resources.

STMicroelectronics Tunis, Tunisia

02-2006 - 12-2007Coordinator

• Implementing Intranet tools used for monitoring the evolution of validation campaigns.

12-2005 - 02-2006Developer

• Validating processors and compilers under different platforms.

GL TRADE

Tunis, Tunisia 08-2005 - 12-2005

Developer & designer

• GL TACTICS: A trader module enhancing the efficiency of the negotiating teams giving them the possibility to customize the implementation strategies and accelerate the decision process.

Please refer to my Linked-in profile for a more complete list of work experiences along with recommendations.

Certificate

IT4IT, Open Group	Score 92%, 12-2016
SABSA Charted Architect, SABSA	11-2016
Big Data Science Trainer, Arcitura	09-2016
Big Data Science Engineer, Arcitura	With Honors, 08-2016
Big Data Professional, Arcitura	With Honors, 05-2016
Archimate Certified, Open Group	Score 82%, 02-2016
Archimate Foundation, Open Group	Score 97%, 02-2016
Cloud Trainer, Arcitura	10-2015
Cloud Architect, Arcitura	With Honors, 10-2015
Cloud Professional, Arcitura	With Honors, 09-2015
Togaf Certified, Open Group	Score 90%, 06-2015
ITIL Foundation, Exin	Score 95%, 06-2015
Togaf Foundation, Open Group	Score 95%, 04-2015
Project Management Professional, PMI	03-2015
SOA Trainer, Arcitura	01-2015
SOA Architect, Arcitura	With Honors, 12-2014
SOA Professional, Arcitura	With Honors, 11-2014
Introduction to Cmmi for development, Cmmi Institute	09-2014
Entrepreneurship for all, EFFECTUATION, EMLYON	Score 75,8%, 01-2014

Principles of Reactive Programming, Coursera	Score 97.5%, 01-2014
MongoDB for DBAs, MongoDB	Score 94%, 11-2013
MongoDb for java, MongoDb	Score 95%, 10-2013
Spring Framework 3, Pivotal	Score 94%, 02-2013
Java 6 Programmer Certified Professional, Oracle	Score 100%, 08-2012
Team Performance, STMicroelectronics	04-2007
English, British Council	4B, 02-2007
GL Certified Professional, GL TRADE	09-2005

Education

National School of Computer ScienceENSI	Tunis,Tunisia
Graduation Project in Computer Engineering	2005
National School of Computer Science ENSI	Tunis, Tunisia
Engineer Degree in Computer Science	2002 – 2005
Tunis Preparatory Institute for Engineering StudiesIPEIT	Tunis, Tunisia
Preparatory Courses (Math Sup, Math Spe)	2000 - 2002
Hannibal	Ariana, Tunisia
(Pre-university Secondary Education)	1994 - 2000

Other Activities

InfoQ Fr Editor

http://www.infoq.com/fr/author/Slim-Ouertani

Founder & Organizer

Riyadh IT Architecture Meetup http://www.meetup.com/Riyadh-IT-Architecture

BLOGGGING

http://java.dzone.com/users/slim.ouertani http://ouertani.github.io http://www.jroller.com/ouertani http://twitter.com/ouertani

INTERVIEW

Paremus, SCA with OSGI, David Savage http://www.prosyst.com/07.02.2009 http://goo.gl/H5yJzY

MAGAZINE

From Microservices to SOA - 20.07.2015 Service Technology Magazine - Issue XCI http://servicetechmag.com/I91/0715-1

STAMPLE

https://stample.co Scala, Akka, Play ElasticSearch, MongoDb, Amazon S3, GreenCloud

OPEN SOURCE

https://github.com/ouertani http://www.reactive-streams.org

Arcitura Authorized Training Partner

http://www.arcitura.com/ Big Data Science, Cloud & SOA

Publications

Pour le fun: for-comprehension à la sauce Java 8	23.07.2015
Vrais ou Faux Jumeaux ?	25.11.2014
Curryfication Java: methods & fonctions	29.07.2014
Des Lenses en Java ?	30.06.2014
Barboter dans le compilateur Java	02.06.2014
Mon Trampoline avec Java 8	18.04.2014
Démystifier les iteratees avec Java	01.11.2013
Le Trio : Akka, Spring et Scala	16.10.2013
Rest with Scala and Vert.x	18.02.2013
Fun with Scala and Vert.x	11.02.2013

Please refer to my Linked-in profile for a more complete list of publications since 2008.

News

Publication de la Nouvelle Spécification d'ArchiMate 3.0	22.06.2016
Java EE et les Anges Gardiens	11.05.2016
Microservice antipatterns à Qcon London 2016	14.04.2016
MongoDB: la magie des Reactive-Streams avec les Capped Collections	21.05.2015
Publication de l'API Reactive Streams 1.0	07.05.2015
Docker, le dernier clou dans le cercueil des serveurs d'applications Java?	19.03.2015

Languages

English, Arabic, French

Written & Spoken